Tea tree oil is touted
as having anti-
fungal properties.
So what happens when
it’s put to the test
against a variety of
fungal infections?
Watch the video
to find out.
"Does Tea Tree Oil Work for Dandruff,
Athlete’s Foot and Nail Fungus?"
Our entire understanding
of the cause of dandruff
shifted with this landmark
article published in 1984.
Instead of relying on secondary sources,
reviews, editorials, opinion pieces,
he looked at the primary literature,
the original studies,
and was amazed to find out how
overwhelming was the evidence
of the true cause, and
how it had been ignored,
because it was so well buried
under the mountain of error,
since some expert in the 1800s
put forth some bogus theory.
We now know that dandruff
is triggered by a fungus
that lives and feeds
on the human scalp,
the two major implications being: first,
how alarming it is that some bogus theory
can remain in the medical literature
unchallenged for a century
despite evidence to the contrary;
and second, hey, if it's a fungus,
what about trying tea tree oil,
which contains components
that have anti-fungal activity
against a range of fungi.
That was based on
studies like this, though,
where tea tree oil in a Petri dish
can fight off pathogenic skin fungi.
But you don't know if it works for
dandruff until you put it to the test.
A hundred and twenty-six men and
women randomized to daily use
of a 5% tea tree oil shampoo
or placebo for a month.
The placebo worked a little bit,
decreasing dandruff
severity by about 10%,
but the tea tree oil shampoo
worked better, about a 40% drop.
Looks like more than
40% from the graph,
but that's because they misleadingly
started the Y-axis at negative 60.
This is a classic deception featured
in chapter 5 of the 1954 classic,
"How to Lie with Statistics."
The graph should really look like this,
which makes the effect less impressive,
but it was still
statistically significant.
Only one patient in the tea tree oil group
actually achieved a complete response,
though one in the
placebo group did as well.
Thus, it seems that tea tree oil shampoo
would require ongoing application
for control of dandruff.
Speaking of fungus, what about tea tree
oil in the treatment of athlete's foot?
That may actually be our most
common fungal skin infection,
affecting up to 1 in 10.
So, about a hundred patients
randomized into one of three groups:
a 10% tea tree oil cream, tinactin, an
antifungal drug, or a placebo cream.
A month later, the fungus was wiped
out in 85% of the drug group,
but only about a quarter of the
placebo and tea tree oil groups.
This is somewhat surprising, since
tea tree oil can kill off the fungus
in a Petri dish, but
apparently not on toes.
That reminds me of some of the
oral health data on tea tree oil.
It can wipe out some oral
pathogens in a Petri dish,
but have people swish a tea tree oil
solution around in their mouth,
and here's the dental plaque buildup
after 4 days of no brushing,
swishing with a placebo.
Here's swishing with a medicated
chlorhexidine mouthwash,
which keeps the
plaque a bit at bay.
But the tea tree oil mouth rinse?
No effect.
So, if tea tree oil doesn't influence
the amount of plaque,
presumably it wouldn't
help with gingivitis,
the gum inflammation that's
caused by plaque buildup.
But, no, here's the twist.
True, no reduction in plaque
with a 2.5% tea tree oil gel.
Yet significant reduction
in gingivitis scores.
Since decreased gum inflammation
occurred without a decrease in plaque,
it appeared to just be helping
more from an anti-inflammatory
rather than
antimicrobial mechanism.
Might the same thing
be happening here?
Yeah, from a mycological cure
standpoint—a fungus cure standpoint—
tea tree oil didn't really do
any better than placebo.
But though the drug wiped out
the fungus in 85% of cases,
in some of those cases, the patients
actually didn't notice an improvement
in symptoms, or they actually
felt worse after the drug,
probably a reflection of
tinactin's irritant side effects.
If instead of mycological cure, you
looked at symptom improvement,
tea tree oil works
as well as the drug.
So, this may be the basis for
the popular use of tea tree oil
in the treatment
of athlete's foot,
but people should realize that
it's just symptomatic relief,
and they're not necessarily
eliminating the underlying cause.
Of course, maybe they didn't use
a strong enough concentration.
And indeed, if you go with not a 10%
cream, but up to 25 or 50%,
you can get mycological cure
rates above that of placebo,
but still not as
good as the drug.
And at those high concentrations, some
of the patients applying tea tree oil
developed moderate to severe
dermatitis—they broke out in a rash.
But, hey, if you
have a patient
that doesn't want to use
the medicated creams,
then a 25% tea tree oil application
has a decent chance
of knocking it out without
being too risky.
But the standard over-the-counter
antifungal creams may work better.
Onychomycosis is a fungal
infection of our nails,
usually toenails, but
sometimes fingernails,
characterized by nail discoloration,
deformity, detachment, thickening,
crumbling, ridging.
Here’s an example of
what it can look like.
Reported prevalence
is estimated
to be about 1
in 25 people,
though it’s more common
in older individuals:
1 in 5 over 60,
and like half of
70-year-olds.
Unfortunately, it’s
really hard to treat,
because the
fungus can hide
deep inside
the nail,
protected from the blood
supply on one side
or anything you
want to put on
topically on
the other.
So, recurrence
after treatment
is common due
to residual fungus,
even if you are able
to beat it back.
Many of the oral systemic
treatments can be toxic,
and many topical
applications
require long
treatment courses,
which may limit
patient compliance,
especially in
patients who want
to use nail
polish or
something to
cover it up.
So, given all
the problems
with a lot of
prescription anti-fungals,
there has been
renewed interest
in natural remedies.
Well, if tea tree
oil can affect
athlete’s foot and
dandruff fungus,
what about
nail fungus?
Well, there was
this study
of a combination of
the antifungal drug
in Lotrimin cream
with tea tree oil
that seemed
pretty effective—
compared to nothing.
But, what about compared
to each other?
Well, there was one
head-to-head study
comparing tea tree
oil with a
common antifungal drug,
a double-blind, randomized
controlled trial:
twice-daily
application of either
the drug or pure
tea tree oil
on the nail
for 6 months.
Debridement was performed
every few months,
where some of
the fungal mass
is debulked, scraped,
ground off.
And, after 6 months,
the drug only
wiped the fungus
out completely
in about 1 in 10 cases,
but looked better,
with partial
or full resolution
of the appearance,
in the majority of
patients either
from the doctor’s assessment
or the patient’s.
And, the tea tree oil
did just as well.
The two preparations
were comparable
in efficacy of cure,
clinical assessment,
and subjective improvement—
even their cost
was comparable.
So, for patients desiring
a “natural” treatment for
athlete’s foot
or nail fungus,
topical tea tree
oil is a reasonable
alternative to
prescription or
over-the-counter
anti-fungals.
Speaking of natural
treatments,
how about a truly
natural treatment.
One potential reason
for the poor
long-term benefits
of any therapy
for nail fungus is
that it may be
only treating
a manifestation
of underlying disease,
such as generalized
immune suppression
or peripheral micro- or
macrovascular disease.
Maybe fungal nail
infections are just
a manifestation of
poor peripheral
blood circulation
that would normally
allow your body’s
natural defenses
to keep the
fungus from
taking root in
the first place.
Evidently, there
was a non-English
language study
of 400 patients
that looked at
the “relationship
between blood circulation
of the skin
and the development
of fungus disease”—
that was the title—and
“found a greater
than 50% reduction
in blood flow
in patients with
[athlete’s foot
and nail fungus]…
compared with patients
without these disorders.”
So, if fungal nail
infections are
just a symptom of
an underlying process,
then treatment
aimed at eradication
of a pathogen may
be unrealistic.
No wonder it just
grows right back.
A more appropriate
goal, then,
may be to just give
up and live with it.
But wait!
If it’s a circulation problem,
why not try to instead
improve the circulation.
We’ve known
since the 1950s
that you can
effectively switch
peripheral artery
circulation on
and off like
a light switch
within days by
switching people
between a low fat
plant-based diet
and the more
conventional diet
that contributed
to the problem
in the first place.